Finding aid to Program for the Studies of Women and Gender records CA.MS.00400
Smith College Archives
Program for the Studies of Women and Gender records
1895-2015
Smith College Archives
Smith College. Women's Studies Program.
CA.MS.00400
4.167 linear feet (5 containers)
This collection contains the records generated by the Program for the Studies of Women and Gender from its founding through 2015. Materials describe the history of the program as well as its publications and various classes and programs.
Biographical / Historical
Building on its origins in women's studies, The Smith College Program for the Studies of Women and Gender continues to examine the experiences, ideologies, works and actions of women in a variety of national, cultural, historical and political contexts. As an interdisciplinary endeavor, the Program for the Study of Women and Gender shows students how different academic disciplines view the operation of gender in the labor market, the family, political systems and cultural production. Research and theory emerge from these everyday realities and feminist theory, in turn, informs our analysis of political choices.
Scope and Contents
These records contain materials describing the history of the program as well as its publications and various classes and programs. Types of materials include agendas, budgets, class materials (syllabi, lecture notes, notes on classes), program meeting minutes, magazine and newspaper articles, notes on conferences, department newsletters, brochures, and publications, as well as material concerning the Junior Year in Women's Studies, and the Meridians journal.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series:
Administration
Faculty
Curriculum
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in the Smith College Archives are open for use, with the following exceptions: "Office Files," files of records created for the use of the administrative unit that created them, are closed to research for a period of 10 years following their creation.
Faculty tenure and promotion files, as well as inactive faculty files are closed permanently. Board of Trustees' records are closed permanently. Minutes of the Faculty Council are closed to all except current Smith College Faculty for a period of 75 years following their creation. Student academic records, student disciplinary records, and all records containing FERPA-covered student information are closed during the lifetime of the student. Student records created 100 years or more ago are assumed to be about deceased students. In all cases, the College Archives will continue to provide public access to materials that were intended to be public at the time of their creation (press releases, publications, etc.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Martha Ackelsberg, professor of Government and Studies of Women and Gender, 1988 - 1989, 2012 - 2013
Marilyn Schuster, professor of French and Studies of Women and Gender, 1986 - 1987, Provost 2009 - 2014
Susan Van Dyne, professor of English and Studies of Women and Gender and chair of the program, 1987 - 1988, 1989 - 1996, 1997 - 2002, 2004 - 2011
Women's studies; Schuster, Marilyn R.; Van Dyne, Susan R.; Ackelsberg, Martha
- SERIES I: Administration
  - Founding Documents, 1970 - ongoing (Box 1)
  - Founding of WST, 1970 - ongoing (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies, 1970 - ongoing (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Advisory Committee, 1970 - ongoing (Box 1)
  - WST clippings (The Sophian), 1970 - ongoing (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 1994 - 1996 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 1993 - 1995 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2004 - 2005 (Box 1)
  - syllabus lunches, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2007 - 2008 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Relations, 1990 - 1997 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 2008 - 2011 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2009 - 2010 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2011 - 2012 (Box 1)
  - table of contents, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2013 - 2014 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Program, 2004 - 2005 (Box 1)
  - chair records, 1987 - 1988 (Box 1)
  - curricular committee, 2005 - 2008 (Box 1)
  - SWG Annual Calendar, 2011 - 2012 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 1980 - 2000 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 1993 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 2001 - 2002 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 2006 - 2011 (Box 1)
  - agendas, 2012 - 2013 (Box 1)
  - minutes, 2002 - 2003 (Box 1)
  - minutes, 2006 - 2007 (Box 1)
  - minutes, 2006 - 2001 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies at Smith for Fran Volkmann, 1982 (Box 1)
  - reports, 1991 - 1994 (Box 1)
  - Junior Year in SWG, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Reduction and Affinities, 2010 (Box 1)
  - membership, 2001; 2003 - 2005 (Box 1)
  - governance and membership, 2005 - 2011 (Box 1)
  - governance and membership, 2007 - 2010 (Box 1)
  - Stimpson on WST, 1980 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1989 - 1991 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1990 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1990 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1990 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1996 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 1996 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 2003 - 2010 (Box 1)
  - self - study, 2012 (Box 1)
  - Crones proposal, 1983; 1991 - 1997 (Box 2)
  - crones proposal, 1999 - 2000 (Box 2)
  - common ground, 2001 - 2006 (Box 2)
  - reaffirming action, 2004 - 2005 (Box 2)
  - reaffirming action, 2004 - 2005 (Box 2)
  - background documents for microclimates project, 2005 (Box 2)
  - affirmative action in employment, 2005 - 2006 (Box 2)
  - microclimate, 2006 (Box 2)
  - common ground r & d, 2006 - 2007 (Box 2)
  - microclimate, 2007 (Box 2)
  - microclimate, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Rutgars Institute for Women's Leadership, 2008 (Box 2)
  - microclimate, 2008 (Box 2)
  - final team meeting for reaffirming action project, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Retreat on Pedagogy, Newton VT, 2001 (Box 2)
  - retreat, 2002 (Box 2)
  - faculty retreats, 2006 - 2007 (Box 2)
  - retreats, 2007 - 2008 (Box 2)
  - SWG retreats, Jan-12 (Box 2)
  - Chairs and Directors retreats, 8/27/2012 (Box 2)
  - SWG retreats, 1/23/2013 (Box 2)
  - SWG funds for research pr conferences, undated (Box 2)
  - NWSA, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Budgets, 1993 (Box 2)
  - mater files, 1997 - 2012 (Box 2)
  - SWG pink, 2004 - 2007 (Box 2)
  - SWG program files, 2008 - 2012 (Box 2)
  - Collett Funds, 2009 - 2010 (Box 2)
  - Budgets, 2009 - 2015 (Box 2)
  - general, 1984 - 1996 (Box 2)
  - staffing, 1992 - 1993 (Box 2)
  - Butler - Haraway Seminar, 1993 (Box 2)
  - joint appointments, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Conway Funds, 1993 - 1999 (Box 2)
  - Susan Van Dyne, 1994; 1996 - 1997; 1999 - 2000 (Box 2)
  - joint appointments, 1997 - ongoing (Box 2)
  - joint appointments, 1998; 2008 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - curriculum and staffing, 1982; 2005 (Box 2)
  - joints, 2004; 2006 (Box 2)
  - searches, 2006 - 2009 (Box 2)
  - queer studies, 2006 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - TT Request, GOV, 2008 - 2010 (Box 2)
  - 2010 Authorization, 2008 - 2010 (Box 2)
  - extra departmental correspondence, 2009 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - recent position requests, 2009 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - QST Plan, 2010 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - Mellon Joint, 2010 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - Mendenhall, 2010 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - joint appointments, 2011 (Box 2)
  - position requests, 2013 - 2014 (Box 2)
  - senior statements, undated (Box 2)
  - prizes and programs, 1980 - 1993 (Box 2)
  - major lists, 1992 - 1993 (Box 2)
  - advising, 2006 - 2011 (Box 2)
  - majors and minors, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Quigley Fellowships, 2007 (Box 2)
  - students, 2007 - 2009 (Box 2)
  - SWG 110: Public Cultures, 2008 (Box 2)
  - SWG Annual Prizes, 2006 (Box 2)
  - SWG/SSC Internships, 2011 (Box 2)
  - Honors, 2011 (Box 2)
  - student liaisons, 2011 - 2012 (Box 2)
- Series II: Faculty
  - Faculty seminar, 1990 (Box 3)
  - "About Women", 3/3/1992 (Box 3)
  - faculty development, 1992 (Box 3)
  - "Gender and Science", 1993; 2001 - 2010 (Box 3)
  - faculty seminar, 1993 - 1994 (Box 3)
  - faculty seminar notes, Jan-94 (Box 3)
  - faculty seminar, 1996 (Box 3)
  - faculty development workshop, 1985 (Box 3)
  - faculty development workshop, 01/1986 (Box 3)
  - "Teaching in the WST Classroom, 1992 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1993 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1994 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1994 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1997 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1998 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1998 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1998 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Post-colonial Residency, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Postcolonial Feminism, Jan-00 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 2000 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 2002 (Box 3)
  - "The Future of Women's Studies, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Homeland (In)Security, 2003 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 2006 - 2007 (Box 3)
  - Exploding Fundamentalisms, 01/2007 (Box 3)
  - January Residency, 2007 - 2011 (Box 3)
  - Ross Nomination, 2008 - 2012 (Box 3)
  - Loretta Ross/Patricia, 2013 (Box 3)
  - Critical Pedagogy Conference, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Pedagogy Workshop, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Pedagogy Workshop, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Five College Workshops, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Five College Workshops, 2012 - 2013 (Box 3)
  - Illegitimate Knowledge, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Illegitimate Knowledge, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Queer Activism/Queer Studies, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Reproductive Justice, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Race, Class, and Culture: Challenges to Feminism, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Reading Gender in History, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Feminist Studies: The Next Stage, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Queer Activism/Queer Studies, 1997 - 1998 (Box 3)
  - Queer Activism/Queer Studies, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Queer Studies, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Kixie Denison, 2005 - 2007 (Box 3)
  - Kixie Denison, 2010 (Box 3)
  - Kixie Denison, 2011 - 2012 (Box 3)
  - Steinem Program, 1996; 2006 (Box 3)
  - C & D Assessment Workshop, 2013 (Box 3)
  - Meridians: feminism, race, and transnationalism, 1984; 2005 - 2006 (Box 3)
  - women's studies publications, 1984. 2004 - 2006 (Box 3)
  - public and media relations, 1993 - 2001 (Box 3)
  - Mother Jones, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Illegitimate Knowledge, 1994 (Box 3)
  - A Culture for the Education of Women, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Smith table, 1996 (Box 3)
  - newsletters, 1998 - 1999 (Box 3)
  - Reaffirming Action, 2004 - 2006 (Box 3)
  - SSC Project, 2008 - 2010 (Box 3)
- Series III: Curriculum
  - general, 2003 - 2008 (Box 4)
  - general, 2007 - 2008 (Box 4)
  - General, 2010 - 2014 (Box 4)
  - archive photographs (duplicates), 1895 - 1983 (Box 4)
  - Thinking About Women, 1979 - 1983 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 1988 - 1993 (Box 4)
  - Gov 364a Feminist Theory, 1993 (Box 4)
  - WST 350b, 1990 (Box 4)
  - seminars, 1992 (Box 4)
  - WST350, 1993 (Box 4)
  - teaching notes, 1994 (Box 4)
  - teaching notes, 1995 - 1996 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 1995 - 1996 (Box 4)
  - feminist political theory notes, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Gov364b: Fem Theory, 1996 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 1997 - 1998 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 1998 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 1999 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 2000 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 2003 (Box 4)
  - course notes, 2005 (Box 5)
  - course notes, 2006 (Box 5)
  - course notes, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Fem Theory Special Studies, 2012 (Box 5)
  - SWG150, 2013 (Box 5)
  - SWG150, 2013 (Box 5)
  - JYA in Women's Studies, undated (Box 5)
  - group meeting, 1982 - 1983 (Box 5)
  - transfers, 1983; 1987; 1990 (Box 5)
  - JYA in Women's Studies, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Women, Race, and Culture, 2004 - 2005; 2007 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1982 (Box 5)
  - Women and Power, 1982 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1982 - 1996 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1982 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1983 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1983 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1984 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1985 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1985 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1986 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1987 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1988 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1990 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1991 (Box 5)
  - course clusters, 1992 (Box 5)
  - policies, 1981 - 1996 (Box 5)
  - SWG honors, 2011 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1980 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1982 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1983 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1983 - 1992 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1984 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1984 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1985 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1986 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1987 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1988 (Box 5)
  - seminars, 1989 (Box 5)